Register of the Rosa Luxemburg and Mathilde Jacob Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- CORRESPONDENCE FILE, 1897-1922
  - Zetkin, Clara to Mathilde Jacob
    - Holograph telegram, 1916 November 20. (Box-folder 3: 62)
    - Holograph letter, 1916 November 20. (Box-folder 3: 63)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1916 November 22. (Box-folder 3: 64)
    - Holograph, 1916 November 28. (Box-folder 3: 65)
    - Holograph, 1916 December 11. (Box-folder 3: 66)
    - Holograph, 1917 January 15. (Box-folder 3: 67)
    - Holograph, 1917 April 6. (Box-folder 3: 68)
    - Holograph, 1917 May 31. (Box-folder 3: 69)
    - Holograph, 1917 June 25. (Box-folder 3: 70)
    - Holograph, 1917 November 4. (Box-folder 3: 71)
    - Holograph, 1917 November 7. (Box-folder 3: 72)
    - Holograph, 1917 November 13. (Box-folder 3: 73)
    - Holograph, 1917 December 15. (Box-folder 3: 74)
    - Typewritten transcript, 1918 January 3. (Box-folder 3: 75)
    - Holograph, 1918 February 9. (Box-folder 3: 76)
    - Holograph, 1918 April 2. (Box-folder 3: 77)
    - Holograph, 1918 June 16. (Box-folder 3: 78)
    - Holograph, 1918 August 27. (Box-folder 3: 79)
    - Holograph (with additional lines by Marta Rosenbaum), 1918 August 29. (Box-folder 3: 80)
    - Holograph, 1918 October 23. (Box-folder 3: 81)
    - Holograph, 1918 November 17. (Box-folder 3: 82)
    - Holograph, 1919 January 18. (Box-folder 3: 83)
    - Holograph, 1919 January 29. (Box-folder 3: 84)
    - Holograph, 1919 February 11. (Box-folder 3: 85)
    - Holograph, 1919 February 21. (Box-folder 3: 86)
    - Holograph, 1919 February 24. (Box-folder 3: 87)
    - Holograph letter, 1919 March 11. (Box-folder 3: 88)
    - Holograph telegram, 1919 March 11. (Box-folder 3: 89)
    - Holograph, 1919 March 12. (Box-folder 3: 90)
    - Holograph, 1919 March 14. (Box-folder 3: 91)
    - Holograph, 1919 March 24. (Box-folder 3: 92)
    - Holograph, 1919 April 10. (Box-folder 3: 93)
    - Holograph, 1919 April 19. (Box-folder 3: 94)
    - Holograph, 1919 April 27. (Box-folder 3: 95)
    - Holograph, 1919 May 3. (Box-folder 3: 96)
    - Holograph, 1919 May 27. (Box-folder 3: 97)
    - Holograph, 1919 May 30. (Box-folder 3: 98)
    - Holograph, 1919 June 4. (Box-folder 3: 99)
    - Holograph, 1919 June 7. (Box-folder 3: 100)
    - Holograph, 1919 June 9. (Box-folder 3: 101)
    - Holograph, 1919 June 10. (Box-folder 3: 102)
    - Holograph, 1919 July 1. (Box-folder 3: 103)
    - Typescript, 1919 July 11. (Box-folder 3: 104)
    - Typescript, 1919 August 23. (Box-folder 3: 105)
    - Holograph, 1919 September 19. (Box-folder 3: 106)
    - Holograph, 1919 September 29. (Box-folder 3: 107)
    - Holograph, 1919 October 2. (Box-folder 3: 108)
    - Holograph, 1919 December 15. (Box-folder 3: 109)
    - Holograph, 1920 March 26. (Box-folder 3: 110)
    - Holograph, 1920 May 6. (Box-folder 3: 111)
    - Holograph, 1920 May 13. (Box-folder 3: 112)
    - Holograph, 1920 May 14. (Box-folder 3: 113)
    - Holograph, 1920 May 28. (Box-folder 3: 114)
    - Holograph and typewritten transcript, 1920 June 26. (Box-folder 3: 115)
    - Holograph, 1920 September 10. (Box-folder 3: 116)
    - Holograph, 1920 September 21. (Box-folder 3: 117)
    - Holograph, 1921 March 30. (Box-folder 3: 118)
    - Holograph, 1921 April 1. (Box-folder 3: 119)
    - Typescript, 1922 October 6. (Box-folder 3: 120)
  - Zetkin, Clara to Luise Kautsky, Typewritten, 1919 April 8. (Box-folder 3: 121)
  - Zetkin, Clara to Inge Keinrath Forster, Holograph, 1919 March 9. (Box-folder 3: 122)
  - Zetkin, Kostia to Rosa Luxemburg and Mathilde Jacob, Two holograph letters, both sent to Mathilde Jacob, one asking her to give the other to Rosa Luxemburg, 1919 January 15 or 16. (Box-folder 3: 123)
- CALENDARS
  General note
  Daily calendars kept by Rosa Luxemburg during her years in prison
  - 1915 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - 1917 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - 1918 (Box-folder 4: 3)
- MEMOIRS
  Mathilde Jacob's "Von Rosa Luxemburg und ihren Freunden, 1914-1919"
  - Version 1 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Version 2 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Version 3 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Version 4 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Fragments (Box-folder 4: 8)
- MISCELLANY, 1887-1919
  Holograph notes, Rosa Luxemburg's school certificate, the Reichsmilitargericht's 1918 decision to keep Rosa Luxemburg incarcerated, tickets to Karl Liebknecht's judicial proceedings and Franz Mehring's funeral, and a handwritten report on a political gathering in Hagan, Germany, and photocopies of letters. Arranged alphabetically by physical form or subject matter.
  - Attest. Rosa Luxemburg's school certificate, 1887 June 14 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Poems by Rosa Luxemburg, Franz Mehring, and Ernst Meyer, thanking Marta Rosenbaum for sending food to several imprisoned Spartakus lesders, Typescripts, 1916 November 14. (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Notes (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Reichsmilitargericht. Decision to keep Rosa Luxemburg incarcerated, 1918 February 22 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Report on the political mass strike and labor unions, Holograph, 1910 October 3. (Box-folder 4: 13)
  - Tickets for funeral of Franz Mehring and judicial proceedings of Karl Liebknecht, respectively, 1919 February 4 and 1916 August 23 (Box-folder 4: 14)
  - Letters of Mathilde Jacob to Jenny Herz, Photocopies of originals in the Archiv der sozialen Demokratie, 1925-1941. (Box-folder 4: 15)
- MICROFILM
  Mathilde Jacob's memoirs, "Von Rosa Luxemburg und ihren Freunden."
  - Mathilde Jacob's "Von Rosa Luxemburg und ihren Freunden, 1914-1919" (Microfilm cabinet)
- PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Two prints of Luxemburg attired in Japanese kimono, five postcards of Luxemburg's profile. (Envelope A)
  - Three postcards of February 16, 1919 demonstration in Munich an five prints of Luxemburg and Liebknecht's grave site. (Envelope B)
  - Three postcards and two prints of Karl Liebknecht throughout his life. One print of Wilhelm Liebknecht's grave site (Karl Liebknecht's father). (Envelope C)
  - Two prints of Leo Jogisches. (Envelope D)
- INCREMENTAL MATERIAL
  - "Sozialdemokratische Korrespondenz," photocopy, 1914 (Box 5)